<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Just Enough Craig</title>
    <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Just Enough Craig</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://justenoughcraig.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rinse and repeat</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April of last year, still in the early days of the pandemic, I quit
using soap in the shower. Because of the social distancing going on at
the time, there would be no better opportunity to try the experiment.
But now, with the hindsight of knowing how trouble-free the experience
was, I wish I had quit soap much sooner. I wish I never started using
soap in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if this sounds like it&amp;#8217;s coming out of left field, understand
there&amp;#8217;s a no-soap health movement going on. The theory is that some of the
stuff that makes up healthy skin gets dissolved and washed away when
using soap and that we&amp;#8217;re better off—or so the theory goes—keeping that
healthy stuff in place. This is analogous to the probiotic and
anti-antibiotic health movement, where the goal is to nurture a diverse
gut biome. The no-soap goal is to nurture a diverse skin biome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does showering entail if there&amp;#8217;s no soap? The answer is showering
becomes a quick rinse-off. For me, I turn on the water and stand in its
stream for a few minutes. I use my bare hands to do some light rubbing,
but mainly I stand there, twisting a bit here and there to effect
different angles with the stream. Then I turn off the water and towel
off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I tried the no-soap technique, I noticed the difference
right away in that I didn&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;feel clean&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, my skin felt
sticky—similar to how it felt before getting into the shower. But the
stickiness went away as I toweled off. By the time I was dry, I felt
clean. Like magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard about the no-soap movement a few years prior and read many
accounts where people raved about it, but I waited until the pandemic to
try it because I had been told to expect a few weeks for my body to
adjust, during which my skin might overreact to the lack of soap and
cause some unpleasant side effects. But for me there was no overreaction
and the improvement was immediate and total—hence my regret for not
trying this sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I still use soap when washing my hands?&lt;/em&gt; Yes. The no-soap thing
isn&amp;#8217;t dogma, and hands are an obvious exception. Also, if, for example,
I got a thick grease stain on my leg, I would use soap to remove the
stain. Grease isn&amp;#8217;t water soluble, so the alternative would be to wait
a couple weeks for the grease to slough off with the skin. Whereas,
nearly all of the ordinary stuff that causes body odor is water soluble,
so a rinse-off is all that&amp;#8217;s needed for ordinary washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I use shampoo?&lt;/em&gt; I still occasionally wash my hair with shampoo—maybe
about once a month. It helps to get the dust out of the hair, but so
does brushing. Overall, I&amp;#8217;m still undecided on the shampoo thing and
figure infrequent shampooing is a good compromise for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I shower more or less frequently now?&lt;/em&gt; It depends. I showered more
frequently in the summer because a cold rinse-off is quick and feels
good. In the winter, I&amp;#8217;ve showered less. One difference I&amp;#8217;ve noticed
after quitting soap is that I become dirty more slowly—probably a direct
consequence of having a more stable skin biome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have any future plans with this&lt;/em&gt; Not really. My only remaining
goal with respect to the no-soap thing is to do some more research to
better understand exactly what&amp;#8217;s going on when using or not using soap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crash and reboot</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten days ago, the day after Christmas, I crashed my bicycle at Tempe
Beach Park going around a slick curve. It was an uncomplicated crash—the
kind I typically get up from with no more harm than some scrapes and
bruises and maybe some shredded Lycra. But I didn&amp;#8217;t get up from this
crash. Not right away, not without tremendous difficulty, and not
without realizing I wasn&amp;#8217;t going to get to the grass five feet away
without crawling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That day couldn&amp;#8217;t have ended soon enough. Shivering in the cold grass
waiting for help, the painful trip to the ER, and the two-hour wait in
the waiting room. Surgery the next day. That five-foot crawl to the
grass turned out to be the easiest move I made over those next
twenty-four hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m now at home nursing a broken femur—technically a hip fracture. I&amp;#8217;ve
got new titanium hardware in my leg, and I&amp;#8217;m using a front-wheeled
walker to get around: cue the old-man jokes. But mostly I&amp;#8217;m lying in bed
with a lot of free time. It&amp;#8217;s great time to reboot &lt;em&gt;Just Enough Craig&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
