<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Just Enough Craig</title>
    <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Just Enough Craig</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://justenoughcraig.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting heart rate right</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-02-01-getting_heart_rate_right/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-02-01-getting_heart_rate_right/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all advice I&amp;#8217;ve read about using heart rate for exercise is
wrong. In this post I&amp;#8217;ll share some of my opinions, which may also be
wrong, but that I think are less wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;olist arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Heart rate monitoring makes sense only in the context of subtracting
out resting heart rate. For example, if you have a resting heart rate of
50bpm and a maximum heart rate of 170bpm, then you have an &lt;strong&gt;maximum
heart rate range&lt;/strong&gt; of 120bpm (170bpm - 50bpm). If your aerobic threshold
heart rate is 155bpm, then you have an &lt;strong&gt;aerobic heart rate range&lt;/strong&gt; of
105bpm (155bpm - 50bpm). Any heart rate that&amp;#8217;s expressed as a percentage
should be a percentage of one of these two values. For example, 75% of
aerobic threshold would be 79bpm (0.75 × 105bpm), which, after we add
back the resting heart rate of 50bpm, results in an actual heart rate of
&lt;strong&gt;129bpm&lt;/strong&gt; (79bpm + 50bpm). That would be your 75% aerobic heart rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;#8217;t makes sense to advise using X% of maximum heart rate, or X%
of threshold heart rate, because both of those values fail to account
for the discrepancies between different people&amp;#8217;s resting heart rate. For
example, if two people both have an aerobic threshold heart rate of
160bpm, but one has a resting heart rate of 40bpm and the other has a
resting heart rate of 60bpm, then the two people will have very
different aerobic heart rate zones. The reason for this is related to my
next point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your aerobic heart rate range linearly correlates with power
output&amp;#8212;&amp;#8203;generally speaking. You can track this firsthand on a bicycle
with a power meter, but it also applies to running and other aerobic
activities. For example, you can track your stable heart rate at
different running paces and then use a running power estimator (such as
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alancouzens.com/blog/Run_Power.html&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;) to see a
linear increase in power as heart rate increases. For example, your
running power should be about 20% higher at 78% of your aerobic heart
rate than it is at 65% of your aerobic heart rate (because 78% is 20%
more than 65%).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardiovascular_drift&#34;&gt;Cardiac drift&lt;/a&gt;
messes up these percentages. Cardiac drift also messes up resting heart
rate. It might be true that the linear correlation between heart rate
and power holds during cardiac drift after accounting for the new,
higher resting heart rate, but that&amp;#8217;s only speculation. In any case, it
wouldn&amp;#8217;t be terribly useful as it&amp;#8217;s impractical to get an accurate
reading for the new resting heart rate during exercise. So cardiac drift
is something that needs to be accounted for, and I&amp;#8217;m still trying to
figure that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My takeaway advice from all this is to scrap published heart rate zones
that say things such as “80% of max heart rate” and instead use the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.trainingpeaks.com/blog/power-training-levels/&#34;&gt;standard
seven-zone model based on power&lt;/a&gt;, then correlate the power numbers to
heart rates when you don&amp;#8217;t have access to a power meter, such as when
running. (Never mind the heart rate percentages specified in that
link—the article gets it wrong, too.) For example, the top of zone 2 is
75% of threshold power, so it correlates to 75% of the threshold heart
rate range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few goals for the year 2021</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-25-goals_for_2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-25-goals_for_2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;olist arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t get COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve made it this far, and the vaccine is so close that this goal is a
no-brainer&amp;#8212;&amp;#8203;even though as a middle-aged, nonessential, stay-at-home
person I&amp;#8217;ll be last in line for the vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kill the grass in my front yard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t see the point in having front-yard grass in Arizona. But I
dislike rock yards, too, so it&amp;#8217;s unclear what final form the yard will
take when the grass is gone. Something involving dirt. As for the
process of killing the grass, I&amp;#8217;m going to try solarization so as to
use herbicide minimally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read at least twenty books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems like this goal should be easily doable if I swap out the time I
normally spend reading idiotic opinions on the Internet and instead read
books written by informed people. Another no-brainer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fitness goals?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prior to breaking my hip in the last week of the year 2020, I had a goal
for 2021 to break one hour on the LMI Trail 100 course, along with a few
other running and biking goals, but now those goals are scrapped. I may
try to match my accomplishment last year of biking and running a total
of 10,000 miles, but doing so will certainly entail more biking and less
running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Log, 2020</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-18-reading_log_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-18-reading_log_2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last year&amp;#8217;s reading list is short. My favorite novel is a toss-up
between &lt;em&gt;2312&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Years of Rice and Salt&lt;/em&gt;, both by Kim Stanley
Robinson, who is my new favorite current author. He blends a creative
and optimistic outlook on things while simultaneously being realistic
about environmental and political problems going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite non-fiction book is &lt;em&gt;The Boys in the Boat&lt;/em&gt;, which is a
breezy but fun account of the eight-oar crew team from the University of
Washington that won the gold at the 1936 Olympics. I&amp;#8217;ll give an
honorable mention to &lt;em&gt;Factfulness&lt;/em&gt;, which is a good reminder to pay
attention to specifics and to facts rather than relying on narratives—a
good lesson especially for the year 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite short story is &lt;a href=&#34;https://poestories.com/read/goldbug&#34;&gt;The Gold
Bug&lt;/a&gt;, by Edgar Allan Poe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the full list of books:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;olist arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&#34;arabic&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2312&lt;/em&gt; by Kim Stanley Robinson (2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To&lt;/em&gt; by Randall Munroe (2019)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Water Knife&lt;/em&gt; by Paulo Bacigalupi (2015)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boys in the Boat&lt;/em&gt; by Daniel James Brown (2013)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Institute&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen King (2019)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Madame Bovary&lt;/em&gt; by Gustave Flaubert (1856)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All Systems Red&lt;/em&gt; by Martha Wells (2017)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rider&lt;/em&gt; by Tim Krabbé (1978)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Years of Rice and Salt&lt;/em&gt; by Kim Stanley Robinson (2002)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind&lt;/em&gt; by Yuval Noah Harari (2017)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Factfulness: Ten Reasons We&amp;#8217;re Wrong About the World — and Why
Things Are Better Than You Think&lt;/em&gt; by Hans Rosling, with Ola Rosling
and Anna Rosling Rönnlund (2018)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rinse and repeat</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In April of last year, still in the early days of the pandemic, I quit
using soap in the shower. Because of the social distancing going on at
the time, there would be no better opportunity to try the experiment.
But now, with the hindsight of knowing how trouble-free the experience
was, I wish I had quit soap much sooner. I wish I never started using
soap in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, if this sounds like it&amp;#8217;s coming out of left field, understand
there&amp;#8217;s a no-soap health movement going on. The theory is that some of the
stuff that makes up healthy skin gets dissolved and washed away when
using soap and that we&amp;#8217;re better off—or so the theory goes—keeping that
healthy stuff in place. This is analogous to the probiotic and
anti-antibiotic health movement, where the goal is to nurture a diverse
gut biome. The no-soap goal is to nurture a diverse skin biome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does showering entail if there&amp;#8217;s no soap? The answer is showering
becomes a quick rinse-off. For me, I turn on the water and stand in its
stream for a few minutes. I use my bare hands to do some light rubbing,
but mainly I stand there, twisting a bit here and there to effect
different angles with the stream. Then I turn off the water and towel
off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I tried the no-soap technique, I noticed the difference
right away in that I didn&amp;#8217;t &lt;em&gt;feel clean&lt;/em&gt;. Instead, my skin felt
sticky—similar to how it felt before getting into the shower. But the
stickiness went away as I toweled off. By the time I was dry, I felt
clean. Like magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I heard about the no-soap movement a few years prior and read many
accounts where people raved about it, but I waited until the pandemic to
try it because I had been told to expect a few weeks for my body to
adjust, during which my skin might overreact to the lack of soap and
cause some unpleasant side effects. But for me there was no overreaction
and the improvement was immediate and total—hence my regret for not
trying this sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few more notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I still use soap when washing my hands?&lt;/em&gt; Yes. The no-soap thing
isn&amp;#8217;t dogma, and hands are an obvious exception. Also, if, for example,
I got a thick grease stain on my leg, I would use soap to remove the
stain. Grease isn&amp;#8217;t water soluble, so the alternative would be to wait
a couple weeks for the grease to slough off with the skin. Whereas,
nearly all of the ordinary stuff that causes body odor is water soluble,
so a rinse-off is all that&amp;#8217;s needed for ordinary washing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I use shampoo?&lt;/em&gt; I still occasionally wash my hair with shampoo—maybe
about once a month. It helps to get the dust out of the hair, but so
does brushing. Overall, I&amp;#8217;m still undecided on the shampoo thing and
figure infrequent shampooing is a good compromise for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I shower more or less frequently now?&lt;/em&gt; It depends. I showered more
frequently in the summer because a cold rinse-off is quick and feels
good. In the winter, I&amp;#8217;ve showered less. One difference I&amp;#8217;ve noticed
after quitting soap is that I become dirty more slowly—probably a direct
consequence of having a more stable skin biome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I have any future plans with this&lt;/em&gt; Not really. My only remaining
goal with respect to the no-soap thing is to do some more research to
better understand exactly what&amp;#8217;s going on when using or not using soap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crash and reboot</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten days ago, the day after Christmas, I crashed my bicycle at Tempe
Beach Park going around a slick curve. It was an uncomplicated crash—the
kind I typically get up from with no more harm than some scrapes and
bruises and maybe some shredded Lycra. But I didn&amp;#8217;t get up from this
crash. Not right away, not without tremendous difficulty, and not
without realizing I wasn&amp;#8217;t going to get to the grass five feet away
without crawling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That day couldn&amp;#8217;t have ended soon enough. Shivering in the cold grass
waiting for help, the painful trip to the ER, and the two-hour wait in
the waiting room. Surgery the next day. That five-foot crawl to the
grass turned out to be the easiest move I made over those next
twenty-four hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;paragraph&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m now at home nursing a broken femur—technically a hip fracture. I&amp;#8217;ve
got new titanium hardware in my leg, and I&amp;#8217;m using a front-wheeled
walker to get around: cue the old-man jokes. But mostly I&amp;#8217;m lying in bed
with a lot of free time. It&amp;#8217;s great time to reboot &lt;em&gt;Just Enough Craig&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
