<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Just Enough Craig</title>
    <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Just Enough Craig</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Log, 2020</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-18-reading_log_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-18-reading_log_2020/</guid>
      <description>Last year&amp;#8217;s reading list is short. My favorite novel is a toss-up between 2312 and The Years of Rice and Salt, both by Kim Stanley Robinson, who is my new favorite current author. He blends a creative and optimistic outlook on things while simultaneously being realistic about environmental and political problems going on.
 My favorite non-fiction book is The Boys in the Boat, which is a breezy but fun account of the eight-oar crew team from the University of Washington that won the gold at the 1936 Olympics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rinse and repeat</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-11-rinse_and_repeat/</guid>
      <description>In April of last year, still in the early days of the pandemic, I quit using soap in the shower. Because of the social distancing going on at the time, there would be no better opportunity to try the experiment. But now, with the hindsight of knowing how trouble-free the experience was, I wish I had quit soap much sooner. I wish I never started using soap in the first place.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crash and reboot</title>
      <link>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://justenoughcraig.github.io/posts/2021-01-04-crash_and_reboot/</guid>
      <description>Ten days ago, the day after Christmas, I crashed my bicycle at Tempe Beach Park going around a slick curve. It was an uncomplicated crash—the kind I typically get up from with no more harm than some scrapes and bruises and maybe some shredded Lycra. But I didn&amp;#8217;t get up from this crash. Not right away, not without tremendous difficulty, and not without realizing I wasn&amp;#8217;t going to get to the grass five feet away without crawling.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>